Ismael Moreno Martinez

Curriculum Vitae

ismael.moreno@eui.eu

CURRENT POSITION

Ph.D. Candidate in Economics

2020 - Present

European University Institute

Supervision: Thomas Crossley & Andrea Ichino

RESEARCH INTEREST

Labor Economics, Household Finances, Applied Economics

WORK IN PROGRESS

Air Pollution and Workplace Safety: Evidence from Dust Precipitation Events (with Benjamin Hattemer)

Our paper presents the first estimates of the economy-wide effect of air pollution on work accidents. We use administrative data on the universe of work accidents reported in Spain. We match municipality-by-day accident counts to information on local particulate matter ambient concentrations and weather variables. We obtain causal estimates by exploiting quasi-random variation in air pollution stemming from dust precipitation. Our estimates imply that an average day of dust precipitation induces a 1.5 percent increase in work accidents. Dust precipitation's impact is more pronounced in days with high anthropogenic air pollution. We find differences in the impact of dust across worker groups based on gender and age. Males and prime-aged workers (25-49 years old) experience the most significant effects.

Fixed-term Contracts and Workplace Safety (with Josep Amer)

Workers under fixed-term contracts have significantly higher accident rates than permanent employees. We use administrative data from Italy and Spain to identify how much of the differential on work accident rates between stems from a contractual effect.

Bank Offices and Household Portfolio Choices (with Jin Cao, Kasper Roszbac and Marina Sanchez del Villar)

We investigate the relationship between temporary job contracts and workplace safety. The aim of this project is to identify how much of the differential on work accident rates between temporary and permanent workers stems from a purely contractual effect.

EDUCATION

MSc in Economics 2018 - 2020

Stockholm School of Economics

BSc in Economics 2011 - 2015

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

PRE-PhD WORK

O. Bover, L. Crespo, C. Gento, and I. Moreno. The Spanish survey of household finances (EFF): description and methods of the 2014 wave. Banco de España Ocassional Paper, (1804), 2018

PROFESSIONAL & TEACHING EXPERIENCE

PhD Internship Programme August - December 2023 Norges Bank Oslo, Norway

Supervisors: Kasper Roszbach & Jin Cao

Teaching Assistant September 2021 - January 2022

SAIS Europe, Johns Hopkins University Bologna, Italy

Professor: Barbara Luppi

Summer Internship June - July 2019

Banco de España Madrid, Spain

Supervisor: Henrique S. Basso

Research Assistant 2016 - 2018

Madrid, Spain Banco de España

The Spanish Survey of Household Finances

Supervisor: Olympia Bover & Laura Crespo

GRANTS & SCHOLARSHIPS

Grant Salvador de Madariaga, Ministerio de Universidades de España. 2020 - 2024

Scholarship for postgraduate studies, Banco de España. 2018 - 2020

Grant for postgraduate studies, Fundación Ramón Areces. (Declined) 2018

SERVICE

Referee: Journal of International Money and Finance

OTHER COURSES & PRESENTATIONS

2nd PhD Summer School on Economic Foundations for Energy and Climate Policies 2021

Universidad Carlos III de Madrid

Introduction to Data Analysis in R

2019

Stockholm School of Economics

XIII Summer School in Public Economics

2017

Georgia State University. Atlanta, GA (US).

Presenting the Survey of Household Finances (EFF) 2014: Methods and Results. Funded by Fundación Rafael del Pino.

Panel Data Econometrics, by Prof. Steve Bond (University of Oxford) 2016 CEMFI Summer School

LANGUAGES

Spanish (native), English (fluent), Portuguese (basic)

COMPUTER SKILLS

Matlab, Stata, R, LATEX